Finding Aid for Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) Staff Files
Bentley Historical Library
Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan). Staff Files
1947-2014
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs.
87365 Bimu B6 2 [2]
570 linear feet (in 571 boxes)
3.4 GB (online)
Central academic administrative unit of the University of Michigan which functions as chief executive assistant to the president, responsible for appointments and promotions with oversight for schools, colleges, educational units and programs; including budget planning, legislative relations, institutional research, and affirmative action policies. The Staff Files subgroup contains the files of individual of vice-presidents, associate and assistant vice-presidents, and other staff members within the vice-president's office.
The Provost's Office (Donor No. 5120 ) makes periodic additions to the records. Records were first received in 1971.
Access to parts of the VPAA record group is restricted based on applicable law and university policy. Restricted material includes personnel files, search files, tenure and review files, grievance and disciplinary files and student files. In addition, the VPAA records are subject to these restrictions
Files of a vice president, or a member of his/her staff, still in office, are restricted.
Files of a vice president or a member of his/her staff, no longer in office, are restricted for ten years from the date of their origin. Files over ten years old are open. This restriction applies to files added to the record group prior to January 1, 2000.
Files added to the record group after January 1, 2000 are restricted for twenty years from the date they were added to the record group, in accord with the access policy for executive officer level records as described below. The VPAA record group does not, as yet, include any records in this category.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files, are restricted for thirty (30) years from the date of their creation.
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Patient/client records are restricted for one-hundred (100) years from the date of their creation. The terms of use for particular records older than 100 years may require the research to sign a Patient/Client Access Agreement.
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
As of 1995 the office represented by this record group is officially titled the Office of the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Previous titles of the office were: Vice Presidents for Academic Affairs and Provost, 1983-1995; Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1962-1983; and Provost, 1938-1962.
Provost
The origins of this office date back to 1938, during President Ruthven's administration, when the position of provost was created by a bylaw of the Board of Regents to "aid the President by performing such of the President's functions as shall from time to time be delegated by him or by the Board of Regents" (Regents' Proceedings, March 1938, p. 505). E. Blythe Stason, the dean of the Law School who had already been performing many of these functions, was appointed the first provost. Stason resigned as provost in November 1944 to devote his attentions to the leadership of the Law School, and James P. Adams, vice president of Brown University and former University of Michigan economics professor, assumed the post of provost and professor of economics in January 1945. At the Regents' meeting of January 1945 the bylaw establishing the provost's position was amended to include the statement that the provost "shall be the chief executive officer of the University next to the President" (Regents' Bylaw 2.02). Adams remained the provost until his resignation in July 1951. A successor to Adams was not named, and the responsibilities of the provost were absorbed by the newly created vice president and dean of faculties, Marvin Niehuss.
Vice President for Academic Affairs
In 1962 two new positions were created in the university administration: executive vice president and vice president for academic affairs.
Marvin Niehuss, vice president for university relations since 1945 and the vice president and dean of faculties since 1951, was promoted to the position of executive vice president in 1962. As vice president and dean of faculties, Niehuss had coordinated university relations with the state legislature and had overseen the administration of the schools, colleges, and other units (including institutes, Extension Service, summer session, and the Reserve Officers' Training Corps), reporting on enrollment, teaching loads, research, and faculty salaries. In his new position as executive vice president, Niehuss continued to supervise legislative relations and served as the University's contact with the state board of education. In addition, the executive vice president was the chief executive assistant to the president and assumed the duties and powers of the president in his absence. (When Niehuss retired in 1968 the position of executive vice president was abolished and a vice president for state relations and planning was established in its place.)
Roger Heyns, a member of the Psychology Department and since 1959 dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, was appointed to the position of vice president for academic affairs in 1962. Heyns assumed many of the duties previously performed by the vice president and dean of faculties. He was given general executive responsibility for the faculty and for the academic programs of the schools, colleges, and other educational units. He reviewed recommendations of deans, directors, and department heads with regard to appointments, promotions, leaves of absence, and salaries of faculty members and special service personnel. In addition, the Offices of Admissions, and Registration and Records--previously under the jurisdiction of the vice president for student affairs--were brought under the vice president for academic affairs.
This reorganization of administrative responsibilities was intended as a means of unifying planning in a period of rapid growth of the University. In actual practice, the duties associated with planning remained dispersed and were shifted from one office to another in the 1960s and 1970s. When a vice presidency for state relations and planning was established in 1968, some of the responsibility for academic program planning was transferred to that office. The Office of Institutional Research, which collected and analyzed data on enrollment trends, faculty characteristics, funding, and related subjects, was transferred in 1969 from Academic Affairs to State Relations and Planning. In 1974 the Office of Institutional Research was renamed the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis and was returned to Academic Affairs, reflecting the assignment of additional evaluation and planning responsibilities under the vice president for academic affairs. Over the course of the 1960s and 1970s, the vice president for academic affairs gradually assumed greater responsibility for budget preparation.
In addition to program and budget planning, the Office of Academic Affairs was involved in implementing affirmative action plans, overseeing the Opportunity Program and Tuskegee-Michigan exchange program, and coordinating support services for minority students.
When Roger Heyns left the university in 1965 to become chancellor of the University of California at Berkeley, he was succeeded by Allan F. Smith, the dean of the Law School. Smith held the post of vice president for academic affairs for nine years and in 1974 was followed by Frank H. T. Rhodes, a professor of geology and since 1971 dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. Rhodes resigned in 1977 to assume the presidency of Cornell University.
Harold T. Shapiro, chairman of the Economics Department, was appointed vice president for academic affairs in 1977 and held the position until 1980, when he became president of the University of Michigan. Alfred Sussman, dean of Rackham School of Graduate Studies, served as acting vice president for academic affairs from November 1, 1979 through July 1, 1980, when Billy E. Frye, professor of Zoology and dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, assumed the position.
Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost
At its February 1983 meeting, the Regents of the University of Michigan changed the title of the position to Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost (hereafter referred to as "provost"). The move to include "provost" in the title was taken in part because of the increased responsibility of the vice president within the university's administration and because of the need to assist the president as he moved into state and national projects, notably the management of the capital campaign fund-raising effort.
In 1986, Billy E. Frye resigned and was replaced by James J. Duderstadt, dean of the College of Engineering, who served as provost until he became the president of the university in September 1988. Robert Holbrook served as interim provost until December 1988. In January 1989, Charles Vest, dean of the College of Engineering, became provost and remained until July 1990, when he left to assume the presidency of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Holbrook served as interim provost for the month of August, after which Gilbert Whitaker, dean of the School of Business Administration, began his tenure as provost.
Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs
In September 1993 the Regents approved a change in title to provost and executive vice president for academic affairs. This title was intended to reflect more accurately the responsibilities of the provost and to "bring Michigan into line with the administrative structures of other universities" (The University Record 49(3), 1993 September 20: 4). The new designation came about when President Duderstadt recommended a change in title for Whitaker. In 1995 Whitaker returned to teaching and was succeeded by J. Bernard Machen, dean of the School of Dentistry. Machen initially served on an interim basis before agreeing to accept a two-year appointment. He did not seek an extension and was succeeded by Nancy Cantor, dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies in 1997.
The position vice provost for academic affairs was created in 1990 to recognize university-wide activities in which John H. D'Arms, dean of Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, was engaged that were beyond the scope of his decanal responsibilities. Such responsibilities included overseeing the Bentley Historical Library and the Clements Library, evaluating promotion and tenure dossiers, and serving as liaison between the university and major foundations (The University Record 45(24), 1990 March 26: 1). With the appointment of new provosts the functional responsibilities and reporting relationships of the vice provost have frequently changed.
Vice Presidents for Academic Affairs and Provost
1962-1965 Roger W. Heyns
1965-1974 Allen F. Smith
1974-1977 Frank H.T. Rhodes
1977-1979 Harold T. Shapiro
1979-1980 Alfred S. Sussman (Interim)
1980-1986 Billy E. Frye
1986-1988 James J. Duderstadt
1988 Robert S. Holbrook (Interim)
1989-1990 Charles M. Vest
1990 Robert S. Holbrook (Interim)
1990-1993 Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs
1993-1995 Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
1996 J. Bernard Machen (interim)
1996-1997 J. Bernard Machen
1997-2001 Nancy Cantor
2001 Lisa Tedesco [Interim]
2002 Paul Courant [Interim]
2002- Paul Courant
Vice Provost for Academic Affairs-Graduate Studies
1990-1995 John H. D'Arms
1996-1997 Nancy Cantor
1998-2004 Earl Lewis
Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs
1993-1995 Lester Monts
Senior Vice Provost for Academic Affairs
2000- Lester Monts
Associate Provosts
1993-1997 Robert Holbrook
1993-1997 Susan Lipschutz
1995-2000 Lester Monts -- Academic and Multicultural Affairs
1997-2001 Paul Courant -- Academic and Budgetary Affairs
1997-2002 Pamela A. Raymond -- Academic and Faculty Affairs
2001- James Hilton -- Academic Information and Instructional Technology Affairs
2002- Janet A. Weiss -- Academic Affairs
2002- Valerie P. Castle -- Academic and Faculty Affairs
Administrative Deans
1962-1974 Robert L. Williams
Assistant Vice Presidents
1974-1982 Edward A. Dougherty
1986 Ralph P. Nichols -- Budget Analysis and Reporting
1982-1995 Robert B. Holmes -- Executive Director M-Quality-1992, Director of Human Resource Development and M-Quality and Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs-1995
1987-1988 Richard L. Fremon -- Budget Analysis and Reporting
1987-1993 Colleen Dolan-Greene -- Personnel
1998 David Schoem -- Academic and Student Affairs
Associate Vice Presidents
1971-1975 John Romani -- Intra-University Programs
1971-1972 William L. Hays -- Academic Development
1974-1981 Richard English -- Academic Services
1975-1981 Carolyne K. Davis -- Intra-University Programs and Facilities
1979-1980 A. Lawrence Fincher -- Analysis and Planning
1981-1993 Robert S. Holbrook -- Academic Affairs
1981-1983 W. Allen Spivey -- Planning and Analysis
1983-1993 Mary Ann Swain -- Academic Affairs
1984-1986 Niara Sudarkasa -- Academic Affairs
2000- Marilyn G. Knepp -- University Budget and Planning -2000, University Budget, Planning and Administration-2002
2000-2003 Barbara Butterfield -- Chief Human Resource Officer-2000, Human Resources and Affirmative Action and Chief Human Resource Officer-2001
2000- Laura M. Patterson -- Administrative Services
Assistant Vice Presidents
1965-1982 Ernest R. Zimmerman -- Academic Services
ca. 1970 and 1973-1987 Robert P. Sauve -- Administration-1970, Special Projects-1973, Budget-1974, Budget Development and Administration-1981
1966-1987 Charles M. Allmand -- Personnel
1968-1973 James E. Lesch -- Budget
1971-1974 Paul A. Spradlin
1971-1972 William P. Fenstemacher
1974/75-1981/82 Edward A. Dougherty -- Special Projects
1980 T. Kushler -- Special Assistant
1981-1985 Ralph P. Nichols -- Budget Analysis and Reporting
1981-1983 Thomas A. Butts
1981-19823 Robert B. Holmes -- Academic Programs
1982-1988 Robin Jacoby
1987-1990 Glenna L. Schweitzer -- Budget Development and Administration
1989-1993 E. Kay Dawson -- Director Academic Human Resources and Special Assistant to the Provost
1990-1991 Eunice Royster-Harper -- Undergraduate Issues
1996-1997 Karen L. Gibbons
1996 G. P. Schrodel -- Special Assistant to the Provost and to the Chief Financial Officer
2000 James Hilton -- Special Assistant to the Provost for Media Rights
Assistant Provosts/Associate Vice Provosts
1995 John H. Matlock --Assistant Vice Provost and Director Office of Academic Multicultural Initiatives-1995, Associate Vice Provost and Director Office of Academic and Multicultural Initiatives-2001
1997-20002 Marilyn G. Knepp -- University Budget and Planning
1999 Linda H. Gillum -- Academic Affairs
1999-2002 Katharine B. Soper -- Academic and Faculty Affairs
2001- Jeffrey R. Frumkin -- Director Academic Human Resources-2001, Director of Academic and Staff Human Resources-2003
2002- Glenda L. Haskell -- Academic and Faculty Affairs
2003- Glenna Schweitzer -- Director of the Office of Budget and Planning
2003- Anthony Walesby -- Senior Director of the Office of Institutional Equity
Administrative Associate to the Provost/Chief of Staff
1990- Karen L. Gibbons -- Admin. Assoc.-1990, Administrative Manager-1993, Chief of Staff-1994
Senior Counselors to the Provost
2002- Pamela Raymond
Policy Coordinator/Advisor
1976-1979, 1983-1986 Virginia B. Nordby
Summary Box Listing
The records of the Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs are organized into three subgroups: Central Files, Staff Files, and Supplemental Files. Each of the subgroups is described in a separate finding aid. The Staff Files subgroup is organized in series for individual staff members. The series may include subseries of Chronological Files, Topical Files, Schools and Colleges and occasionally other files. The records of an individual staff member were often received in a number of separate accessions. For this finding aid, all the files of a staff member have been brought together to reflect the intellectual organization of the records rather than their physical arrangement in boxes. As a consequence, the box numbers may not be in numerical order.
1 Ernest Zimerman
2-22 Carolyne K. Davis
22-23 Edward A. Dougherty
24-30 Richard A. English
31-42 Robert L. Williams
42-53 John H. Romani
53-54 Mary Ann Swain
55 Carolyne K. Davis
56-59 Robert S. Holbrook
59 W. Allen Spivey
59-60 Mary Ann Swain
60-65 Robert B. Holmes
65-68 Niara Sudarkasa
68 Robin Jacoby
69-101 Robert S. Holbrook
102-114 Robert B. Holmes
115 Robert Sauve
116-148 Mary Ann Swain
149-166 Robert S. Holbrook
167-185 Robert B. Holmes
186-189 Niara Sudarkasa
189-200 Mary Ann Swain
201-236 Robert S. Holbrook
236-245 Robert B. Holmes
245-247 Mary Ann Swain
247-252 E. Kay Dawson
253-263 Robert S. Holbrook
264-277 Robert B. Holmes
277-285 Restricted Files
286-293 Mary Ann Swain
294 Restricted Files
295 Mary Ann Swain
296-350 Robert S. Holbrook
351-365 Susan S. Lipschutz
366-382 Paul A. Courant and Marilyn Knepp
382-385 Paul A. Courant
386-388 Mary Ann Swain
389-390 E. Kay Dawson
390-395 Robert B. Holmes
395-399 Pamela Raymond
400-402 Katharine Soper
403-409 Karen S. Gibbon
410-411 Restricted Files
412-414 Robert S. Holbrook
414-416 John Godfrey
416 Nancy Cantor
417-418 E. Kay Dawson
419-421 A. Lawrence Fincher and Raplh P. Nichols
421-424 Pamela Raymond
425 Valerie Castle
426 Glenda Haskell
426-431 Linda Gillum
431 Janet Weiss
431-432 Mary Ann Swain
432 Ben van der Plijm
433 Sharron Schmidt
433-434 Kathleen Bauer and James Hilton
434 Katharine Soper
434-438 Stephanie Riegle
438 Catherine Shaw
438-439 Paul A. Courant
439-447 Marilyn Knepp
447-465 Paul A. Courant and Marilyn Knepp
466-469 Phil Hanlon and Marilyn Knepp
469-475 Phil Hanlon, Teresa Sullivan, and Anne Berens
475-477 Phil Hanlon
477-498 Karen Gibbons
498 Brian Gonz
498 John King
499-501 Phil Hanlon and Anne Berens
501-502 Phil Hanlon and Teresa Sullivan
502 Phil Hanlon and Marilyn Knepp
5035 Anne Berens
503 Kathleen Bauer
503-505 Stephanie Riegle
505 A. Lawrence Fincher and Ralph P. Nichols
505-547 Lester P. Monts
548-552 Restricted Files
553-554 Lester P. Monts
555-558 Karen Gibbons
559-563 Philip Hanlon, Martha E. Pollack, and Anne Berens
564-567 Philip Hanlon, Lori Haskins, and Ron Fitzgerald
568-569 Philip Hanlon, Martha E. Pollack, Lori Haskins, and Ron Fitzgerald
570 Philip Hanlon and Martha E. Pollack
571 Philip Hanlon
571 Anne Berens
The Staff Files subgroup of the record group Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs consists of 570 linear feet and spans the years from 1947 to 2013. The Staff Files subgroup is comprised of the records of the associate and assistant vice presidents for academic affairs. Whereas the records of the Central Files subgroup often contain finished products, such as reports and policy statements, the Staff Files subgroup tends to document the process of policy formation and other decision-making functions. Scattered through the associate and assistant vice presidents' papers, for example, are frank statements of opinion regarding various schools and programs, candidates for promotion, and the relationship between the branches of the university, as well as notes on meetings with faculty members, committee activities, and other subjects.
The Staff Files subgroup includes the records of the following past and current associate and assistant vice presidents, listed in the order in which their records first appear in the boxlist: Ernest R. Zimmermann, Carolyne K. Davis, Edward A. Dougherty, Richard A. English, Robert L. Williams, John H. Romani, Mary Ann Swain, Robert S. Holbrook, W. Allen Spivey, Robert B. Holmes, Niara Sudarkasa, Robin Jacoby, Robert Sauve, E. Kay Dawson, Susan Lipschutz, Paul Courant, Marilyn Knepp, Pamela A. Raymond, Katharine Soper, Karen Gibbons, John Godfrey, Nancy Cantor, A. Lawrence Fincher, Ralph P. Nichols, Valerie Castle, Glenda Haskell, Linda Gillum, Janet Weiss, Ben van der Plijm, Sharon Schmidt, Kathleen (Kati) Bauer, James Hilton, Stephanie Riegle, Catherine Shaw, Philip Hanlon, Teresa Sullivan, Anne Berens, Brian Konz, John King, Lester Monts, Martha E. Pollack, Lori Haskins, and Ron Fitzgerald. The records of an individual, while still in office, are received by the archives on an ongoing basis.